To demonstrate routing, I'm back in this little blog application which we created, where we render blog
Rotay gstermek iin, blog gnderilerini bir blog yazs seebileceiniz ve burada
posts, can select a blog post and where we can also create a new post.
yeni bir yaz oluturabildiimiz yerlerde oluturduumuz bu kk blok uygulamasna geri dndk.
Right now, that's all sitting in on one and the same page
u anda hepsi ayn sayfada oturuyor.
and this of course is not really the user experience we want to provide.
Ve bu elbette gerekten sunmak istediimiz kullanc deneyimi deildir.
Instead we probably want to show some links at the top to allow the user to switch between pages and
Bunun yerine, kullancnn sayfalar arasnda gei yapmasn ve farkl sayfalar yklemesini salamak iin st ksmda
well load different pages.
baz balantlar gstermek istiyoruz.
So let's start by adding these links before we start implementing routing and supporting these different
Dolaysyla, ynlendirmeyi uygulamaya balamadan ve bu farkl balantlar desteklemeden nce bu balantlar
links.
ekleyerek balayalm.
Now the links can simply be added to the blog container and you could of course also outsource them
Artk balantlar sadece blok konteynerine eklenebilir ve elbette bunlar kendi bileenlerine d
into their own component
kaynak olarak verebilirsiniz.
but I want to keep this lean so that I can focus on the routing functionality.
Ancak ynlendirme ilevselliine odaklanabilmek iin bu eilimi korumak istiyorum.
We will then see a real world set up in the next module where we apply routing to our course project.
Ardndan, bir sonraki Mart aynda kurulacak gerek bir dnya greceiz ve burada ders projemize ynlendirme uyguluyoruz.
So in our render method, I not only want to output my posts but above the posts, I want to have some
Dolaysyla render yntemlerimde yalnzca yazlarm ktmz deil, baz stbilgiyi de isteyeceim yazlarn
header where I also output some links, so I'll add a header here and in there,
stnde istiyorum, burada baz balantlar ktracam, bylece burada bir stbilgi ekleyeceim.
My nav element
Benim tavsiyem
and there we typically have an unordered list which then in turn contains our links inside list items
Ve genelde listemizde duyulmam bir listemiz var, l srayla liste elerindeki balantlar ieriyor.
and for now I'll simply add them like well normal links simply.
imdilik basit balantlar basite ekleyeceim.
So there we have probably our home link which will be that starting page which shows all the posts we
Dolaysyla, muhtemelen ev halkmza ait olan, bizim sahip olduumuz tm mesajlar gsteren balang
have,
sayfas olacaktr.
then we might have a link for a single post and this is something we will create dynamically so forward
Ardndan, tek bir yayn iin bir balantmz olabilir ve bu, iletileri dinamik olarak ileriye doru ileti dizisi
posts
oluturacaz.
we load it, and the last thing I want to have here in the navigation is the new post link which
Ykledik ve navigasyonda burada olmasn istediim en son ey, yeni yaynlar kesebilecek veya
could lead to /new-posts or something like that.
byle bir ey yapacak bir balant yaynlamyor musunuz?
So this is how we now set up our links,
Artk balantlarmz byle kurduk.
now let me add some styling so that they don't look super ugly. For that I'll
imdi bana Daddles iin sofrank brokoli bulamayacak ekilde biraz ekillendirme yapalm.
first of all quickly style the unordered list to have no default list style, so the margin and padding of 0,
Her eyden nce hzla stil DIANORA listesinin varsaylan liste stiline sahip olmamasn salayn, bylece Ciro'nun kenar boluu ve
I'll then also style
dolgusu da stildir.
any list items in my posts components here in the end which I have, so this blog component, there the list
Postalarmdaki tm liste eleri sahip olduum sonum ve bu blok bileeni,
items should use the inline-block style and have a margin of maybe 20px around them and the links
liste elerinin satr ii blok stilini kullanmas ve belki de 20 piksel kenar boluuna sahip olmalar ve
in there, the anchor tags. I'll remove the text decoration so set this to none, give them a color of black.
D-NC'lerindeki balantlarn tm kaldrlan etiketlerdir dekorasyon bylece diski siyah olmayan bir renk vermek iin ayarlayn.
Now let's see how that looks like, if we go back,
imdi geri dnersek nasl olacan grelim.
we see that here at the top, the reason for this of course is that I have a little error.
Gryorsunuz, burada en stte tabii ki bunun nedeni kk bir hatam olmasdr.
Posts is applied to this first section,
Bu ilk blme yaynlar uygulanr.
I'll need to set an overall class name of blog
Hepsinin blok snfnn genel bir snf adn belirlemesi gerekir.
maybe here on the wrapping div and then the css file. Therefore, I'll replace posts with blog here for the
Belki burada Ploc'la olan tm yer deitirme maddeleri iin buradaki asfalt olarak sarma div ve
navigational aid items.
NDC zerinde yer alr.
So now we get the links here,
imdi balantlar alyoruz.
let's maybe also center them, I'll set a width of 100% for the unordered list and then set text
Belli bal ortalamalar sralamasz listede yzde 100 olacak ekilde ayarladktan
align center so that the links are now centered.
sonra metin ortalamasn ayarlayarak balantlarn ortalanmas salansn.
Now let's maybe also add a little hover style so blog a hover and blog a active can now get a color
fareyle zerine gelip engelle karlatracaz ve etkin bir kiinin artk turuncu renkte olan 2:41 F renk alabiliyoruz.
of maybe #fa923 which is an orange color.
imdi biraz havada kalma stili de ekleyelim, bylece
Now with that, we got our links.
imdi bununla balantlarmz aldk.
That's of course nice but clicking these doesn't really do much,
Elbette gzel ama hzl Indie's pek fazla ey yapmyor.
It loads different
Farkl ykler.
URLs
Sen.
as you can see in the URL bar,
Grdn gibi, sen de Albar'sn.
but it doesn't affect our application.
Ancak uygulamanz etkilemez.
Actually it always returns to same page.
Aslnda her zaman ayn sayfaya dner.
This is related to the way our development server is set up and your production server should also
Bu, gelitirme sunucumuzun kurulma biimiyle mi ilgili ve retim sunucunuzun da kurulmas gerektii anlamna
be set up.
m geliyor?
It always returns the index.html file for every route because for the server, there are no different
Her rota iin deceim dizin HVM'yi her zaman dndrr nk sunucu iin farkl yollar yoktur,
routes, there is only one single file
yalnzca tek bir dosya vardr.
it has return all the time.
Her zaman geri dnd.
It's now about parsing that URL in the client.
Artk istemcide olduunuzu ayrtrmakla ilgili.
This is what we'll start working on next by adding the router package and setting up different routes.
Ynlendirici paketini ekleyerek ve farkl rotalar kurarak bir sonraki aamada almaya balayacak olan ey budur.